מזל טוב. Mazel tov. Today is דף יומי Daf Yomi today's מכות
י"ז, Makkot Yud Zayin, דף Daf 17. We pick up at the
bottom of ט"ז עמוד ב' Tet Zayin Amud Bet at the two
dots, about ten lines from the bottom. So we're going through the
different cases in the משנה Mishnah that get מלקות malkos after a
long whole classic discussion about לאו הניתק לעשה lav hanitak la'aseh and
ביטלו ולא ביטלו, bitlo ve-lo bitlo, קיימו ולא קיימו. kimo ve-lo kimo.
How do you actively מבטל mevatel the מצוה mitzvah of of divorcing
a not divorcing the wife and in
the case of the rape and so on? And then how you
actively מבטל mevatel the מצוה mitzvah of not remarrying her? Fascinating suggestions
in the גמרא. Gemara. Anyway, and then we moved on to the
case of of eating non-kosher food and one of these classic discussions
of the גמרא Gemara about multiple
עבירות, aveiros, sometimes for eating particular bugs or insects or whatnot. And
also an important discussion about בל תשקצו, Bal Teshaktzu, don't abominate yourself,
which the גמרא Gemara focuses on particularly on sort of eating eating
repulsive things or even things that are not exactly eating, like drinking
from a vessel that was used in the process of bloodletting, although
I guess you're winding up eating the blood in the process. But
anyway, so that was a fascinating little digression. Important though, in general,
for this concept of בל תשקצו. Bal Teshaktzu. Okay, and now the
גמרא Gemara turns to the case in the משנה, Mishnah, which is
the eating of טבל tevel and of other types of grains that
have not had the תרומות ומעשרות terumos u'ma'asros taken from it. Okay,
or eating from מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni out of ירושלים Yerushalayim that
hasn't been redeemed and so on. So let's take a look. Again,
ten lines from the bottom. ט"ז עמוד ב'. Tet Zayin Amud Bet.
אכל טבל ומעשר ראשון. Achal Tevel u'Ma'aser Rishon. אמר רב: Amar Rav:
אכל טבל שהוא מעשר עני, Achal Tevel she-hu Ma'aser Ani, לוקה. lokeh.
Now
what if the classic טבל tevel doesn't have the תרומה terumah taken
from it? Or doesn't have מעשר ראשון Ma'aser Rishon taken from it,
which has in it תרומת מעשר? Terumas Ma'aser? And the תרומה terumah
is the most weighty thing. The תרומה, terumah, if you eat תרומה,
terumah, that's also like a חייב מיתה בידי שמים. chayav misah bidei
shamayim. So you know, similarly like a טבל tevel is like a
חייב מיתה בידי שמים. chayav misah bidei shamayim. So how bad though
is טבל tevel when the only and the thing not removed from
it is something that even once removed has no איסור issur status,
like so again, if you haven't removed the תרומה, terumah, the תרומה
terumah has איסור issur status. If you haven't removed the מעשר ראשון,
Ma'aser Rishon, well the מעשר ראשון Ma'aser Rishon in it has תרומת
מעשר terumas ma'aser which has an איסור issur status, it's forbidden for
non-כהנים. Kohanim. If you haven't removed the מעשר שני, Ma'aser Sheni, well
the מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni is אסור assur to eat out of
ירושלים. Yerushalayim. But let's say you've taken out everything and it's a
year that's not מעשר שני, Ma'aser Sheni, it's a year that it's
מעשר עני. Ma'aser Ani.
So in that type of a case, right, even after you take
the מעשר עני Ma'aser Ani out from it, there's no איסור issur
status, it just belongs to the עניים. aniyim. So how bad is
it to eat the טבל tevel in that case, like maybe it's
a form of
a גזל, gezel, but do you really get lashes? So that's the
question. So רב יוסף Rav Yosef says, yes, you do.
Or רב Rav says, אכל טבל שהוא מעשר עני Achal Tevel she-hu
Ma'aser Ani לוקה, lokeh, you do get מלקות malkos even if the
only thing not taken from it is מעשר עני. Ma'aser Ani. כמאן,
Keman, who's this going like? היא תנא, Hi tanna, like the following
תנא, Tanna, דתניא, d'tanya, as it's taught in a ברייתא: braitah: אמר
רבי יוסי, Amar Rabbi Yosei, יכול לא יהא חייב אלא על טבל
שלא הורם ממנו כל עיקר? yachol lo yehei chayav ela al tevel
she-lo huram mimenu kol ikkar? Maybe the only thing that you transgress
and get lashes is טבל tevel that hasn't had anything, any of
the מעשרות ma'asros taken from it. הורם ממנו תרומה גדולה ולא הורם
מעשר ראשון, Huram mimenu terumah gedolah ve-lo huram ma'aser rishon, let's say
תרומה גדולה terumah gedolah was taken but not the first tithe, or
מעשר ראשון ולא מעשר שני, ma'aser rishon ve-lo ma'aser sheni, the first
tithe and not the second tithe, ואפילו מעשר עני, ve-afilu ma'aser ani,
so all of those have like I say a certain type of
a קדושה kedushah or an איסור issur status. But how do I
know even if the only thing not taken from the טבל tevel
is the מעשר עני? Ma'aser Ani? Again, you don't have the מעשר
עני Ma'aser Ani the same years as you have the מעשר שני.
Ma'aser Sheni. But anyway, the only thing not taken from it is
something that is property of the עניים aniyim but does has no
איסור issur status. How do I know you get lashes? תלמוד לומר,
Talmud lomar, לא תוכל לאכול בשעריך מעשר דגנך תירושך ויצהרך וכל lo
suchal le'echol bish'arecha ma'asar deganecha tiroshcha ve-yitzharecha ve-chol etc. etc.
a whole list of things that are בשעריך bish'arecha in your gates,
means outside of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, in your cities. Okay, it's not clear
there that it's talking about טבל tevel or that it's talking about
טבל tevel without מעשר עני Ma'aser Ani taken. But ולהלן הוא אומר,
ulehalan hu omer, later it says, ואכלו בשעריך ושבעו. ve-achlu bish'arecha ve-save'u.
That's when it speaks about giving the מעשר עני Ma'aser Ani to
the poor, the poor will eat בשעריך bish'arecha in your gates, in
your cities, and they'll be satisfied. מה להלן מעשר עני, Mah halan
Ma'aser Ani, the same way there over there the בשעריך bish'arecha is
referring to מעשר עני, Ma'aser Ani, אף כאן מעשר עני, af kan
Ma'aser Ani, here too מעשר עני. Ma'aser Ani. So when it says
לא תוכל לאכול בשעריך מעשר, lo suchal le'echol bish'arecha ma'asar, the מעשר,
ma'asar, if by- based on the link of the word, it includes
the case of מעשר עני. Ma'aser Ani. Now there's obviously no prohibition
of eating מעשר עני Ma'aser Ani out of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So the
only thing it could mean that you can't eat and there's a
negative prohibition of eating relating to מעשר עני Ma'aser Ani would mean
טבל tevel that doesn't have מעשר עני Ma'aser Ani separated from it.
Okay, so included in the משנה'ס Mishnah's case of טבל tevel getting
lashes is even the weakest form of טבל. tevel. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara continues. אמר רחמנא לא
תוכל, Amar Rachmana lo suchal, you cannot, you're not able, you're not
allowed to eat. Okay, אמר רב אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav אמר
רב יוסף Amar Rav Yosef, כתנאי, kitnai, this is a debate of
תנאים. Tannaim. רבי אליעזר אומר אין צריך לקרות אותו שם על מעשר
עני של דמאי וחכמים אומרים קורא אותו שם ואינו צריך להפריש, Rabbi
Eliezer omer ein tzarich likros oso shem al Maaser Ani shel demai
vachachamim omrim korei oso shem ve'eino tzarich lehafrish, top of י"ז עמוד
א'. Yud Zayin Amud Aleph.
So דמאי demai is grain that you buy from the עם הארץ,
Am Haaretz, from like the farmers, you know, עם הארץ Am Haaretz
just means sort of like the, you know, the what do you
call it the salt of the earth. But anyway often it has
a derogatory connotation associated with it but it also just means like
you know the people out there that are working on the farms
and so on. And the problem is that you know is that
it was determined that they are not, you know the גמרא Gemara
attributes this to יוחנן כהן גדול, Yochanan Kohen Gadol, he sent and
he did a whole survey and he determined that they were not
taking תרומות ומעשרות trumos u'maasros from their grain because obviously that's you
know you lose twenty percent of your produce so they were just
selling it without תרומות ומעשרות trumos u'maasros taken from it. The one
thing they took was תרומה גדולה truma gedola because תרומה גדולה truma
gedola is even one grain for an entire storehouse. So that they
were careful to take. Also it's like the weightiest of the sins,
you know eating תרומה truma and so on. Okay, so therefore any
grain you buy from an עם הארץ Am Haaretz from somebody who
you don't know is careful about their stuff is called דמאי, demai,
doubtful grain. And the rabbis required you to take you know מעשר
ראשון, maaser rishon, מעשר שני, maaser sheni, the only thing you don't
have to take is תרומה. truma. Okay now if it is a
מעשר... maaser... now but because there's a question whether they took we
don't know they definitely didn't take right.
There's a good chance they
didn't take. So therefore if let's say I go ahead and I
buy this grain and I separate out I don't have to separate
תרומה truma I separate out מעשר ראשון. maaser rishon. Okay now what
do I do with that מעשר ראשון? maaser rishon? Well normally I
would give it to a לוי Levi but I don't really know
that I'm obligated so you know then it becomes a ממון mamon
issue, then it becomes a property debate. This לוי, Levi, Joe, let's
say Mike over here who is a לוי, Levi, he says give
me that מעשר ראשון. maaser rishon. Joe's a לוי, Levi, Joe's a
לוי Levi says give me give me that
מעשר ראשון maaser rishon from the grain I bought from Mike that
I separated out. I say I don't know for all I know
Mike took מעשר ראשון. maaser rishon. I'm just doing it to be
safe. I'm not going to give it to you I'm going to
eat it myself. And that's the principle of המוציא מחבירו עליו הראיה
Hamotzi mechavero alav hara'aya that when it becomes a monetary issue not
an איסור issur issue. For an איסור issur issue I have to
be safe and separate it out so it won't be טבל. Tevel.
But for a monetary issue I say prove to me it's yours.
You can't prove it I'm going to keep it. The only problem
is I can't eat the מעשר ראשון maaser rishon because the מעשר
ראשון maaser rishon has in it תרומת מעשר trumas maaser and that's
all if it really is מעשר ראשון. maaser rishon. And that's really
an איסור, issur, right. So what I do so that's what I'm
going to do. Okay except תרומת מעשר trumas maaser has to be
a tenth, תרומת מעשר trumas maaser is not a tiny bit it's
מעשר מן המעשר. maaser min hamaaser. Right, so that's exactly what I
do. I separate out my מעשר ראשון maaser rishon from the grain
I bought from Mike which is like you know let's say I
bought a hundred units I separate out ten units. Of those ten
units I separate out one that's תרומת מעשר. trumas maaser. That okay
I don't you know I can give to a כהן Kohen you
know whatever that I take care of I'm not going to eat
that. Okay but the other nine units that's worst-case scenario it's מעשר
maaser that belongs to Joe but it's permitted for me to eat
because תרומת מעשר trumas maaser was taken. Since Joe can't prove it
I'm going to eat it. That's what I do with the מעשר
ראשון. maaser rishon. מעשר שני maaser sheni okay I separate it out
and now if it is מעשר שני maaser sheni I have to
eat it in ירושלים Yerushalayim so then I have to redeem it
and so on. מעשר עני maaser ani I separate out, there's no
תרומת מעשר. trumas maaser. So here you know Gloria comes and she's
in charge of collecting for the עניים aniim and she says give
me the מעשר עני maaser ani and I say prove it belongs
to the עניים. aniim. You can't prove it. Same המוציא מחבירו עליו
הראיה. Hamotzi mechavero alav hara'aya. I get to eat the מעשר עני.
maaser ani. Okay but I have to separate it out or else
the grain is טבל. Tevel. So now רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says
you don't even have to declare any part of the grain מעשר
עני. maaser ani. You can just eat it without declaring it from
this case of דמאי. demai. So you basically he says you don't
have to separate out מעשר עני maaser ani of
דמאי. demai. וחכמים אומרים, Vachachamim omrim, the sages say no קורא שם.
korei shem. If I have this big pile I have to say
you know ten units actually nine units because it's ten percent of
what's left so there was a hundred I took ten for מעשר
ראשון maaser rishon there's ninety left. So I say nine units over
there in the southern corner is מעשר עני. maaser ani. ואינו צריך
להפריש, ve'eino tzarich lehafrish, I don't have to separate it out though
because
I'm allowed to eat the whole thing. I can eat the remaining
grain and I can eat the מעשר עני. maaser ani. Everybody sort
of get that point? Okay. Which
contradicts רב. Rav. Yeah okay well we're going now wait we're going
to talk about how this fits into רב, Rav, okay. Here's my
big pile of grain I separate... we had a hundred units I
separate out ten this was מעשר ראשון maaser rishon okay from this
I separate out one that was תרומת מעשר trumas maaser okay and
then this I'm going to eat because worst-case scenario it belongs to
a לוי Levi and then it's just a monetary issue and I
say go prove that it's yours this was דמאי. demai. Now this
is left to ninety okay I say this nine units here is
מעשר עני maaser ani but I don't have to separate it out
because I'm allowed to eat the whole thing. This I had to
separate out in order to identify the תרומת מעשר trumas maaser etc.
But here once I call it מעשר עני maaser ani then this
stops being this goes from being טבל. Tevel. to now being to
just now being grain, okay, I fixed it from its טבל tevel
state because I finished separating out the מעשרות, maasers, and now I
can just go ahead and eat the whole thing. I don't have
to separate it. That's what the חכמים Chachamim say. That makes sense.
The question is figuring out the position of who has the first
position, רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, who says I don't even have to
designate מעשר עני. maaser ani. So the גמרא: Gemara: why not? I
have טבל tevel here. מעשר עני maaser ani is mixed in. So
the גמרא Gemara says: oh, maybe he disagrees with the earlier statement
that we just said. And he says that it's not a, you
do not transgress טבל tevel with מעשר עני maaser ani if it's
mixed in. That even if you don't separate out מעשר עני, maaser
ani, the worst you're doing when you eat it without it being
separated out is that you're stealing from the עניים. aniyim. Not like
that's okay, but the point is it's not טבל. tevel. How else
would he say you don't have to declare this מעשר עני? maaser
ani? Before you declare this מעשר עני, maaser ani, the whole thing
was טבל. tevel. So if he says you don't have to even
declare it מעשר עני, maaser ani, it sounds like he's saying that
it does not have a status of טבל. tevel. Wait, wait, let's
just read it, okay?
ומאי לאו בהא קמיפלגי. u'mai lav b'ha kamiflagi. It seems that this
is the debate. מר סבר ודאי טוב לה ומר סבר ודאי לא
טוב לה. mar savar vadai tuv lah u'mar savar vadai lo tuv
lah.
That it must be that the חכמים Chachamim who say you have
to designate the מעשר עני maaser ani even though you don't have
to physically separate it, they say when it's not דמאי, demai, when
it's ודאי טבל, vadai tevel, when it's ודאי, vadai, מעשר עני maaser
ani mixed in makes it real טבל tevel and you would get
lashes. So here that it's a ספק, safek, you still have to
separate it out, you know, at least verbally. The other one holds,
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer holds: no, even if it was ודאי vadai
grain with once the only thing left is מעשר עני, maaser ani,
then it's not an איסור issur status and it's no longer טבל.
tevel. You have to separate it to give it to the עניים,
aniyim, but it's no longer טבל. tevel. That would be the only
explanation why he would say you don't have to designate it. So
the גמרא Gemara says: אמר ליה אביי אי הכי אדמיפלגי בספיקו ליפלגו
בודאי. amar leih Abaye ei hachi adamiflagi b'sfeiko liflgu b'vadai. No,
cause then they should have a more direct argument. That would be
a much more interesting argument. Don't start have some debate about דמאי.
demai. Actually have that direct debate. Have רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer say:
if you have טבל, tevel, טבל ודאי, tevel vadai, after you've separated
out everything else, it stops being טבל, tevel, you know, when the
מעשר עני maaser ani is left, okay, and if you eat it
you don't transgress. Let him say that, okay. They're not saying that.
So it sounds like when it's definitely טבל tevel they agree that
it's a problem. So then what's, how does this work? והכא בהא
קמיפלגי. v'hacha b'ha kamiflagi. Here's how they debate. מר סבר לא נחשדו
עמי הארץ על מעשר עני של דמאי. mar savar lo nechshdu amei
ha'aretz al maaser ani shel demai. Ah,
cause רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says: you know why you don't have
to separate this out? Because even though I think that the עמי
הארץ amei ha'aretz don't take מעשר ראשון maaser rishon or מעשר שני,
maaser sheni, I think they do take מעשר עני. maaser ani. Now
that would be strange. What would motivate, you know, one of these
farmers to say "I'm not going to bother with מעשר ראשון maaser
rishon or מעשר שני, maaser sheni, I only care about the עניים,
aniyim, the poor, I don't want to steal from charity." Right, so
let's take a look. Okay. כיון דממונא הוא אפרושי מפריש. keivan d'mamona
hu afrushei mafrish. Okay.
Now רש"י Rashi says, let's go רש"י, Rashi, if you look at
רש"י, Rashi, so you might think it's because they have more sympathy
towards the poor or something. Maybe some of their friend farmers are
poor or something like that. Look at רש"י Rashi six lines down
in the narrow lines. אפרושי מפריש ליה ולאפוקי טיבליה, afrushei mafrish leih
u'l'afukei tivleih,
they do it to get out of the טבל tevel status. נהי
דמעשר ראשון לא מפריש דסבר אם מפרישינא רמינן לאפרושי תרומת מעשר מיניה
ושהיא במיתה ונותנה לכהן, nehi d'maaser rishon lo mafrish d'savar im mafrishina
ramina l'afrushei terumas maaser mineih v'she'hi b'misa v'nosnah l'kohen, ומעשר שני נמי
אי מפריש ליה בעי לאסוקיה ומיכליה בירושלים. u'maaser sheni nami ei mafrish
leih bei l'asokeih u'michleih b'Yerushalayim.
So it sounds like what רש"י Rashi is saying is the following.
Not like they care for the poor. But they say like this:
look, I'll sep— it's the opposite. It's like if it's only a
monetary issue, it's not a big sin. Okay. So they say מעשר
עני maaser ani I'll separate and therefore I'll eat it myself. Alright,
I'm stealing from the עניים, aniyim, big deal, it's just stealing, it's
just בין אדם לחבירו, bein adam l'chavero, you know, that's what they'll
say. And therefore, so since I can a little bit fix the
טבל tevel status and I'll separate it and then that won't create
any, then it'll just be a גזל gezel problem, that I'll do.
It's like a little funny logic. Okay. But if the way to
fix the טבל tevel status is to separate מעשר שני maaser sheni
and that's going to require me to eat it in ירושלים, Yerushalayim,
or to separate מעשר ראשון maaser rishon and that's going to require
me to deal with תרומת מעשר terumas maaser and give that to
a כהן, kohen, then that's like more איסור issur headache, I don't
want to worry about it. But this solves a little bit of
an איסור issur problem, a little bit, because it takes out a
part of the מעשר maaser without creating new איסור issur obligations on
me. Just creating like ממונות mamonus obligations on me. That seems to
be the logic, okay. ומר סבר. u'mar savar. Let's read that. מר
סבר לא נחשדו עמי הארץ על מעשר עני של דמאי. mar savar
lo nechshdu amei ha'aretz al maaser ani shel demai. They actually take
מעשר עני, maaser ani, so that's why when you buy it from
the farmers you don't have to take it. Not because it's not
a problem, but because you can assume it was already taken. כיון
דממונא הוא אפרושי מפריש, keivan d'mamona hu afrushei mafrish, they separate. ורבנן
סברי: v'Rabbanan savri: no, כיון דטרחא ליה מילתא לא מפריש. keivan d'tarcha
leih milsa lo mafrish. No, they don't bother. The one little grain
of תרומה terumah for everything they do. Anything more is too much
of a pain and they don't bother with it, okay. So bottom
line is they're saying this debate is a debate about the nature
of דמאי, demai, how much by דמאי demai we have to be
afraid that there's still מעשר עני maaser ani mixed in, but at
least the assertion is that everybody agrees if there's definitely מעשר עני
maaser ani mixed in, it still is טבל tevel and you would...
Still get lashes. Two questions. The one is instead of separating out
the ten and taking one from that, can't you leave it all
in there since you're gonna eat the nine of it anyway and
say, I'm just gonna separate the תרומת מעשר Terumat Ma'aser from it
and just keep it all together? If you designated it. You could
sort of say, you can't just take one.
You can't take תרומת מעשר Terumat Ma'aser without having מעשר. Ma'aser. But
what you could do is you could say these ten are מעשר
Ma'aser and leave it there and then take that one. Right. But
you do have to designate a particular ten. Then the other question
is, to these days, would we say things has gotten worse, so
if you go to wherever it is in Israel, don't you actually
need to separate תרומות Terumot also? Well that becomes a whole issue
about like if you go straight to the farm, but that becomes
a whole issue about like... Or you buy it in the שוק
shuk somewhere. Yeah, so that I'm not going to get into practical
issues right now, but it becomes a whole issue about like you
know about to what degree the רבנות Rabbanut sort of you know
does like oversees the whole process and makes sure that תרומות ומעשרות
Terumot U'Ma'asrot are taken from everything and whatever, depends on like who...
Or maybe they don't oversee it at all? I mean, we don't
say that like, oh fine, עם הארץ Am Ha'aretz took תרומה, Terumah,
I don't have to take תרומה Terumah anymore.
You mean if somebody is not סומך somech on the רבנות Rabbanut
thing or they're going it straight to a farm and they're whatever,
I don't I so I don't know, it's a good question. Like
do we still assume that people who aren't doing it are at
least doing תרומה? Terumah? Yeah I don't know.
Okay, so now let's continue. The משנה Mishnah says like this. Okay.
כמה יאכל מן הטבל? Kama Yochal Min HaTevel? How much eat from
the טבל? Tevel? So now we have a famous debate that רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says even a even this well it's not going
on the טבל Tevel part. Yeah, even the smallest amount, even like
one grain. And the חכמים Chachamim say no, no, no, you need
a כזית, kezayit, like normal, of course you need a כזית. kezayit.
And he says wait, one grain is כבריאתו. kebriato. One grain is
in its natural state and therefore, you know, somehow it's like a
full unit and therefore you should be חייב chayav even the less
than a כזית. kezayit. So this is the idea, you know, the
כזית kezayit is just a quantity. Why should I need to eat
a certain quantity? If the תורה Torah says don't חזיר chazir and
I eat a little חזיר, chazir, I ate חזיר. chazir. Why should
it matter if I ate more? Less.
So there's different ways of understanding it, it's not called חזיר, chazir,
it's not called eating, but to some degree it's not significant enough,
okay, to deserve maybe one way of saying it is did I
eat חזיר chazir but not I didn't do it bad enough to
deserve a punishment? A whole range of ways of saying is it
bad enough or not. Okay. But what רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer seems
to be saying is, okay, so one way of measuring bad enough
is quantity, right? You ate more than a certain minimum amount. That
you know somehow could be under the radar. But if it's quality,
if it's somehow it's something qualitatively significant, it's a whole grain, okay,
you know then maybe that would deserve a, you know, maybe that
would be doing something significant even if it's not quantity. I'm not
so impressed by eating a whole grain. I understand. So maybe a
whole ant might be different, and that you had in the גמרא
Gemara yesterday, so we'll get to that. Okay. But you know, it's
an interesting question like about ברכה אחרונה. beracha achrona. Like let's say
you ate a whole I don't know
grape or a whole what would be a small type of a
thing that you could eat? A berry. Well fig's pretty big. Less
than a כזית. kezayit. A whole one raspberry... no, one blueberry, okay?
Would you make a ברכה אחרונה? beracha achrona? Is it significant because
it's a whole sort of... Is that a sort of satiation? In
which case you're not really sated. Maybe, or maybe that's that's a
good question about what ברכה אחרונה beracha achrona is based on. Is
it based on the act of eating, how much is that connected
to the question of like of this. Anyway let's take a look.
So that's the debate in the משנה. Mishnah. כמה יאכל מן הטבל?
Kama Yochal Min HaTevel? אמר רב ביבי אמר רבי שמעון בן לקיש
Amar Rav Bibi Amar Rabbi Shimon Ben Lakish מחלוקת בחיטה אחת. Machloket
Bechita Achat. Their debating when you eat a grain, you one piece
of grain. One what's it called, not piece, one kernel of grain.
אבל בקמח, Aval Bekemach, if you're eating flour, דברי הכל כזית. Divrei
Hakol Kezayit. Then of course everybody agrees that there's a minimum amount,
right? It's to his idea was an idea called בריה. biryah. Okay,
which we haven't said yet. Well, the משנה Mishnah says
כבריאתו. kebriato. רבי ירמיה אמר רבי שמעון בן לקיש Rabbi Yirmiyah Amar
Rabbi Shimon Ben Lakish כמחלוקת בזו כך מחלוקת בזו. Kemachloket Bezu Kach
Machloket Bezu. No, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer would say even if it's
a little bit of flour, he has no minimum to get lashes.
So it's a general principle, whenever it deals with lashes at least
by forbidden foods, like you know presumably there are minimums by other
things, it's always an interesting question, normally we speak about a שיעור
shiur of things, right? But at least when it says by foods
and maybe by other things, no minimum, lashes for everybody. Lashes for
everybody.
תנן. Tenan. אמר להם רבי שמעון. Amar Lahem Rabbi Shimon. אי אתם
מודים לי באוכל נמלה שכל שהוא שחייב? Ee Atem Modim Li Be'ochel
Nemala Shekol Shehu Shechayav? They he said to them, look, here I'll
prove to you that even eating a little bit of the טבל
Tevel you're חייב chayav because you agree that if you eat one
ant you get lashes. אמרו לו מפני שהוא כברייתו. Amru Lo Mipnei
Shehu Kevriyato. They say yeah, but that's because that's in the original
way it was created, that's a whole unit. אמר להם. Amar Lahem.
He said back to them, אף חיטה אחת כברייתו. Af Chita Achat
Kevriyato. So one one one kernel of grain is a whole unit.
What's the difference? So it sounds like he's saying only if it's
a kernel of grain in its whole form, not if it's flour.
So the גמרא Gemara says, חיטה אין קמח לא. Chita In Kemach
Lo. That sounds like he's only saying he does have a minimum,
it's just that he says that a whole unit one kernel counts
as a significant unit, not flour. No, the גמרא's Gemara answer is
לדבריהם קאמר. Lidvraihem Ka'amar. No, no, he's saying back to them within
your logic you should agree about
one kernel.
לדידי, Ledidi, as far as
I'm... Even grain is not a—even grain is the smallest amount. I
don't have a minimum amount.
אלא לדידכו, Ela l'didchu, but you, that you believe there is a
minimum amount, אודו לי מיהת דחיטה אחת כבריה הויא, odo li mihat
d'chitah achat k'biryah havya, for you at least, if you say there
is a minimum, the same way one ant is a minimum, one
kernel of grain should be a minimum. And ורבנן V'rabbanan and the
rabbis would say back, ברית נשמה חשובה חטה לא חשובה. Briyas neshamah
chashuvah, chitah lo chashuvah. No, no, no, a living creature is significant.
Something that was once alive. Something that was not once alive is
not significant, okay? If it's inanimate, then a whole unit of grain
is not as significant as a whole ant, okay? תניא כוותיה דרבי
ירמיה, Tanya k'vasei d'Rabbi Yirmeyah, we taught like—that's their distinction. Yes, we
agree with an ant, we do not agree by a grain. Now,
we taught like Rabbi Yirmeyah, that Rabbi Eliezer himself does not really
hold of a minimum idea at all. He was just arguing the
rabbis within their logic. I'm sorry, I keep on saying Rabbi Eliezer,
it's Rabbi Shimon. רבי שמעון אומר כל שהוא למלקות. Rabbi Shimon omer
kol shehu l'malkos. The smallest amount, there is no minimum amount to
get lashes. Lashes, if you transgressed, I don't care even you ate
one tiny speck of flour. Okay. לא אמר כזית אלא לענין קרבן.
Lo amar k'zayis ela l'inyan korban. The minimum amount is to bring
a קרבן, korban, which is fascinating. Like, you would think, if it's
a קרבן korban and between me and God and the fact that
I sinned and it's something more metaphysical, or whatever, maybe it would,
maybe God's a little more forgiving, maybe it would have to be
a certain amount, right? I'm sorry, excuse me, the opposite. Maybe it's
like, okay, a sin is a sin, a sin is a sin,
but for the court to punish me, for it to be deserving
of an actual, like for me to feel guilty about it, I've
got good Jewish guilt, I can feel guilty about anything. So for
me to feel like it's guilty and it's a sin and I
should bring a קרבן, korban, maybe I would say even no minimum,
even the tiniest amount. But for me to be deserving for בית
דין Beis Din to come and to employ its resources and for
the society to sort of condemn it and to physically punish me,
you would think that would require a minimum. So it's very bizarre
that he sort of flips it and that he, or whatever, flips,
but he says it this way. And some of you, you go
to פחות משווה פרוטה, pachos m'shaveh perutah, yeah, then you get lashes.
Yeah, so it's true. Anyway, so for Rabbi Shimon, there is no
minimum for getting lashes. So, and it's now, and is that limited
to food? Maybe it's not even limited to food, I don't know.
Like would he say, if you're not allowed to, like, cut your,
what's a case, like you're not allowed to cut your פאות peyos
or whatever, like would he say if you cut like even one
hair? If you cut like, would it be by all איסורים issurim
that there's no minimum at all? I don't know. By a מלאכה
melachah on יום טוב, Yom Tov, right? If you even like carried
a speck of dirt—well carrying is allowed on יום טוב. Yom Tov.
Anyway, if you did בורר borer on a tiny amount, like is
by everything... בורר borer is also probably okay. Anyway,
whatever it is, anyway, would he just, would he really say this
across the board or is it just by eating? It's not clear.
Anyway, that's Rabbi Shimon's position according to this ברייתא braisa that there's
no minimum amount for lashes. Let me say something about what do
you call it, about the issue of בריה. biryah. Why is it,
what is the difference for the rabbis between the grain and the
ant? So one way to say it is just it's this issue
of qualitative significance. Something that was alive has greater qualitative significance than
something that was inanimate. Okay, then, but then it gets to an
interesting question about what about something that was part of something that
was not alive, but itself was not alive? What? So תוספות Tosafos
says, or תוספות Tosafos brings in a whole discussion in the גמרא,
Gemara, this is more about questions of ביטול, bitul, but whatever, a
גיד הנשה. gid hanasheh. על כן לא יאכלו בני ישראל את גיד
הנשה. al kein lo yochlu b'nei Yisrael es gid hanasheh. Okay, so
is, is that גיד הנשה, gid hanasheh, I mean I guess if
you have a tiny little baby animal that has a tiny גיד
הנשה gid hanasheh that's less than a כזית. kzayis. Okay, or whatever,
okay, is that significant because it was part of a live animal,
or is it not significant because it itself was not alive? So
but one way of saying it is that having been alive gives
it qualitative significance. But the other way of saying it, תוספות Tosafos
points out, and this I like better, it's more logical, is that
the real issue between the ant and the wheat was not that
one was alive or not, bracketing what it sounds like in the
גמרא. Gemara. It's how the תורה Torah expresses the prohibition. When the
תורה Torah says, don't eat a שרץ, sheretz, what's the פסוק? pasuk?
Like, what
we just had it yesterday,
כל שרץ העוף טמא
הוא לכם לא יאכלו. kol sheretz ha'of tamei hu lachem lo ye'acheilu.
Okay, so don't eat a שרץ. sheretz. Well if I ate an
ant, I ate a שרץ. sheretz. That is exactly the thing the
תורה Torah said not to eat. Don't eat an insect, I ate
an insect. Okay, so don't eat a גיד הנשה. gid hanasheh. I
ate a גיד הנשה. gid hanasheh. So it's the exact thing the
תורה Torah said. But when the תורה Torah says don't eat טבל,
tevel, okay, טבל tevel is not a defined unit, right? There's a
little bit of it, a lot of it, it's not a, right?
A טבל tevel is like, you know, don't eat חזיר. chazir. If
I ate a whole pig, okay, I ate חזיר, chazir, but if
I ate some of the flesh of a pig, I didn't, I
ate some of חזיר, chazir, I didn't eat a whole unit. Okay.
And therefore when, when it's not the unit as described in the
תורה, Torah, it's a quantitative amount but not the unit as described
in the תורה, Torah, then you need a certain quantitative amount. Okay,
does everybody understand? It's very different. One is just like, oh, it
has qualitative significance. It's a whole thing and it was and it
was alive. The other is, it's not because of that, it's because
this is exactly the object the תורה Torah said not to eat.
And the תורה Torah defined a well-defined object and this was the
entirety of that well-defined object. And when you did not eat a
well-defined object, you ate just something that there's more or less of,
but not, you know, fewer or, there's, what is it? It's, what's
the difference? Greater and fewer? Yeah, it's like more or less as
opposed to, it depends if you're talking about like discrete or versus
like quantity. Right. So that's it. When it's a discrete thing and
it's the discrete thing the תורה Torah said not to eat and
I ate the whole discrete thing, then that doesn't need a שיעור.
shiur. But when it's not discrete, then I need a שיעור. shiur.
Okay? Fewer people, fewer, right. Right, right. Okay, exactly. All right, can
you just remind me one time, like, you know, as to why
we do בריתא Briyata with a תו tav instead of בריתא Briyata
with an אלף? alef? I don't know. I don't know. You have
no person. Okay? Now if you take a look at תוספות, Tosafot,
look at תוספות Tosafot three lines
down, he expresses this idea of a whole unit. Three lines in
the narrow line. תוספות Tosafot says, הטעם תלוי דכל שהוא בשמו כשנחתך
הוי בריה. Hatam talui dikol she-u-be-shmo keshenechtach havei berya.
One of the ways of identifying a whole unit is if you
cut it in half, does it, is it called the same thing?
Okay? וניחא מנבילה שאינה אובדת שמה שלפעמים אם נחתכה נשארת נבילה. Unicha
mineveilah she-eino ovedes shemo she-lefamim im nechtacha nisheret neveilah.
Right,
if you have like נבילה neveilah or חזיר chazer or טבל tevel
and you cut whatever unit you have in half, I still have
טבל. tevel. I have more טבל tevel or less טבל, tevel, more
חזיר chazer or less חזיר. chazer. Okay? But when I cut a,
an ant in half, I don't have a, I don't have an
ant anymore. I have a half. So what's worse than finding? Yeah,
exactly. All right, let's take a look now at the next משנה.
Mishna. Okay. האוכל ביכורים. Ha'ochel Bikurim. Okay,
next משנה Mishna about things you get lashes. האוכל ביכורים עד שלא
קרא עליהם. Ha'ochel Bikurim ad shelo kara aleihem.
If you eat ביכורים Bikurim before you did the, you know, ארמי
אובד אבי. Arami Oved Avi. Okay, now by the way, ביכורים Bikurim
is like תרומה, terumah, only a כהן Cohen is allowed to eat
ביכורים. Bikurim. So this really means a כהן Cohen ate from it
before the ארמי אובד אבי. Arami Oved Avi. You've already taken it.
Meaning... You've taken it, you've brought the כהן, Cohen, like this קרא
kara is not like designating like we just mentioned before. You brought
the ביכורים Bikurim to the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, you gave it,
you put it down, you gave it to the כהן, Cohen, and
you didn't say ארמי אובד אבי Arami Oved Avi and the כהן
Cohen was so starving that he ate from it beforehand. Okay? קדשי
קדשים חוץ לקלעים. Kodshei kodashim chutz le-klaim. Or you ate קרבנות korbanot
of the holiest ones. This is again a כהן Cohen eats it.
He's allowed to eat a חטאת, chatas, that would be a classic
example inside the grounds of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, but he
ate it out of the grounds of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash,
out of the עזרה. Azarah. You said the האוכל ביכורים ha'ochel Bikurim
is the כהן Cohen not you? What would be the difference? Right.
No, you it's definitely, but even the כהן. Cohen. Even if a
כהן Cohen is normally allowed to eat these things in the right
circumstances, if he ate them in the wrong time or the wrong
place, he gets lashes. Okay. קדשים קלים Kodshim kalim now, the lighter
קרבנות, korbanot, like the שלמים, shelumim, which you're allowed to eat, but
you're only allowed to eat it in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, and you ate
it out of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. ומעשר שני U'maaser sheni also מעשר שני,
maaser sheni, you're allowed to eat in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Okay, חוץ לחומה,
chutz lachoma, outside the walls of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. השובר את העצם בפסח
הטהור. Hashover es ha'etzem be-pesach ha-tahor. If you broke a bone with
a פסח Pesach that was טהור tahor because and was able to
be eaten. וכל עצם לא תשברו בו, V'chol etzem lo tishberu bo,
the דרשה drasha is בו בטהור ולא בטמא. bo be-tahor v'lo be-tamei.
Okay. If you anyway weren't allowed to eat the קרבן פסח Korban
Pesach because it got טמא tamei and you broke a bone, you
don't get lashes. But if it was a פסח Pesach you were
allowed to and had a מצוה mitzvah to eat and instead you
broke and instead but maybe while you were eating it you broke
a bone, then you get lashes. Okay. וכל עצם לא תשברו בו.
V'chol etzem lo tishberu bo. הרי
זה לוקה. Harei ze lokei. You get lashes ארבעים. arbaim. אבל
המותר בטהור, Aval hamotar be-tahor, if you leave over from the from
a כשר, kosher, from a טהור tahor קרבן, korban, okay, you leave
over the meat and you don't eat it, which is a negative
prohibition, right? לא תותירו ממנו עד בוקר. Lo sosiru mimenu ad boker.
והשובר בטמא, Ve'hashover be-tamei, or you break a bone in a פסח
Pesach that cannot be eaten, that's טמא. tamei. Wait, you're talking about
a פסח, Pesach, you're not just any קרבן, korban, right? המותר בטהור's
Hamotar be-tahor any קרבן. korban. No, it's any קרבן. korban. Okay, אינו
לוקה עליהם, eino lokei aleihem, you do not get. Now, the טמא
tamei is because that's just not the prohibition. The prohibition is only
breaking a bone in a פסח Pesach that you're that you that
you're able to and have a מצוה mitzvah to eat. But the
reason you don't get lashes for leaving over, we discussed that like
two days ago, that was because it is a לאו שאין בו
מעשה. lav she-ein bo ma'aseh. You're passive in it. Okay? And that's
why even though נותר notar is a transgression, or it could be
because it's ניתק לעשה, nitak l'aseh, then you're supposed to burn it
the next morning. Okay? Or התראת ספק. hatra'as safeik. There's a lot
of reasons why by נותר notar you don't get lashes. Okay. הנוטל
אם על הבנים, Hanotel em al habanim, ah, the classic, finally, the
mother bird with the chicks or, רבי יהודה אומר לוקה ואינו משלח.
Rebbi Yehuda omer lokei ve-eino meshaleiach. You get lashes, sending it away
will not help you. The מצוה mitzvah to send it away is
not a ניתק לעשה. nitak l'aseh. It's not coming to fix it.
It's an it's a separate מצוה. mitzvah. You should have already sent
it away. Okay? It's conceptually it's קודם, kodem, even though it appears
after, right? He would say conceptually this is something you're supposed to
do before sending rather than taking it is you're supposed to... send
it away. Once you transgressed, it doesn't get fixed by sending it
away. וחכמים אומרים, v'chachamim omrim, חכמים chachamim say משלח ואינו לוקה. meshaleach
v'eino lokeh. No, you send it away and you don't get lashes.
זה כלל, zeh klal, this is the principle, כל מצות לא תעשה
שיש בה קום עשה, kol mitzvas lo sa'ase sheyesh bah kum asei,
there's a מצות עשה mitzvas asei that's coming to stand up like
stand up and do to fix it, to fix it, אין חייבין
עליה, ein chayavin aleha, you're not liable and that's what we just
had two days of discussing about קימו kimo and בטלו bitlo and
the whole thing. Okay, let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara.
אמר רבא בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן זו דברי רבי עקיבא
סתימא עשאה. Amar Rabba bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan zu divrei
Rabbi Akiva stima asa'ah. This סתם משנה stam Mishnah is going like
רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, okay? אבל חכמים אומרים ביכורים הנחה מעכבת בהן
קריאה אין מעכבת בהן. Aval chachamim omrim bikurim hanacha me'akeves bahen kria
ein me'akeves bahen. Yes, the כהן Kohen would transgress by eating the
ביכורים bikurim too soon, but the too soon is before you actually
placed it down before the מזבח, mizbeach, right? והנחתו לפני מזבח השם
אלוקיך. vehanchato lifnei mizbeach Hashem elokecha. Okay, so the, but if you
did do the placing down and you just did not do the
declaration, then that does, that declaration is not at the end of
the day prevent it, the permissibility we're going to see, from it
being eaten. Okay, ולימא זו דברי, V'leima zu divrei, it's going to,
like it'll be tomorrow's דף, daf, how we're going to learn out
the דרשות drashos of whether it's the declaration that makes it permissible
or the placing down. ולימא זו דברי רבי שמעון סתימתאה? V'leima zu
divrei Rabbi Shimon stimata'ah? Why do you say that the סתם משנה
stam Mishnah is רבי עקיבא? Rabbi Akiva? Say the סתם משנה stam
Mishnah is רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. Okay, הא קמשמע לן דרבי עקיבא
כרבי שמעון סבירא ליה. Ha kamashma lan d'Rabbi Akiva k'Rabbi Shimon sevira
lei. This is telling you that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is going
like רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. Now, isn't that funny? I thought רבי
שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, wasn't רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon one of the תלמידים
talmidim of רבי עקיבא? Rabbi Akiva? Right? רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, רבי
מאיר, Rabbi Meir, רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, those are all תלמידי רבי
עקיבא, talmidei Rabbi Akiva, right? Anyway, okay, but they're the same position.
Really, it's רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is going like רבי עקיבא. Rabbi
Akiva. But the reason we want to focus on רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon is because, is because yes, we'll see later of the רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva position about whether declaration is what מתירs matir it
or is it the putting it down. That's the one thing we're
focusing on. Is it the declaration or the putting it down. But
now we're going to spend the rest of today's דף daf focusing
on a ברייתא braisa with רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, where he not
only makes this point about that it's the declaration that prepare, that
permits it to be eaten, the ביכורים, bikurim, but he's going to
go through a whole פסוק pasuk and basically lay out how we
know you get מלקות malkus for a whole wide range of things
before the, you know, that if they're not exactly in the situation
where they're ready to be eaten, that you get מלקות malkus for.
And that's going to be a whole big ברייתא braisa for רבי
שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. So since that is like a position that clearly
identifies a whole list of מלקות, malkus, some of which are mentioned
in our משנה, Mishnah, we want to sort of bring in the
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon position. Okay? So there's two things going on
here. One is a position of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and now
we're saying רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, that the lack of declaration prevents
it from being
eaten. And not the putting it down. You need to do the
declaration. And the other thing is the very fact that you get
מלקות. malkus. How do I know you get מלקות malkus for this
stuff? That's going to be this ברייתא braisa for רבי שמעון. Rabbi
Shimon. So let's take a look. Okay, מאי רבי שמעון? Mai Rabbi
Shimon? Who's the רבי שמעון? Rabbi Shimon? This is really what we
wanted to get to. דתניא. Detanya. Okay, now this is all going
to be a long דרשה drasha of one פסוק. pasuk. So what's
the פסוק? pasuk? It's דברים יב. Devarim yud-beis. It's this לא תוכל
לאכול בשעריך. Lo suchal leechol bish'arecha. We quoted it earlier by טבל
tevel of
מעשר
שני, ma'aser sheni,
here. לא תוכל לאכול בשעריך. Lo suchal leechol bish'arecha. These are things
you're not allowed to eat. So what are they?
מעשר
דגנך, ma'aser degancha, תירושך, tiroshcha, ויצהרך. v'yitzharecha. Okay, so that's מעשר ma'aser
from different things. Remember what we said before was that referred to
טבל tevel that didn't have מעשר שני ma'aser sheni taken from it,
at least that's what we said earlier. Okay, excuse me, מעשר עני
ma'aser ani taken from it, even if
מעשר עני ma'aser ani
wasn't taken. Yes. ובכורות בקרך
וצאנך, uvechoros bekarcha v'tzonecha, וכל נדריך אשר תדור, v'chol nedarecha asher tidor,
ונדבותיך v'nidvosecha
ותרומת ידך. utrumas yadecha. So what we are going to say is,
so the פשט pshat of this פסוק pasuk is all of these
are things that have to be eaten in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So מעשר
ma'aser if you're talking about מעשר שני, ma'aser sheni, בכורות bechoros is
קרבנות korbanos has to be eaten in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. נדריך Nedarecha is
other קרבנות korbanos like a שלמים, shlamim, קדשים קלים. kodashim kalim. נדבותיך,
Nidvosecha, other קרבנות. korbanos. Okay. ותרומת ידך Utrumas yadecha would be, now
that's a little doesn't work. It's not like תרומה, terumah, but it
would be like ביכורים. bikurim. ביכורים Bikurim
is often called תרומה. terumah. So the פשט pshat of this פסוק
pasuk is these are all things that have to be eaten in
ירושלים. Yerushalayim. What we're going to do is we're going to focus
on each word, and each word is going to tell us not
just things that have to be eaten in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, but things
that
if they're not eaten in their right way, you get lashes for
them. And it's not specifically about eating in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, okay? Let's
take a look at this. Okay, where were we? דתניא ותרומת ידך
אלו ביכורים, Detanya: Utrumas yadecha eiluh bikurim, אמר רבי שמעון, Amar Rabbi
Shimon, מה זה ל mah zeh l... דתניא detanya ותרומת ידך u-terumat
yadecha אלו ביכורים. eilu bikkurim. אמר רבי
שמעון, מה
בא
זה ללמדנו? Amar Rebbe Shimon ma ba zeh lelamdenu? What is this
coming to teach us? אם לאוכלן חוץ לחומה, Im le'ochlan chutz lachomah,
you're not allowed to eat ביכורים bikkurim outside of the wall of
ירושלים, Yerushalayim, קל וחומר ממעשר קל! kal vachomer mima'aser kal! I can
learn it out from מעשר שני. Ma'aser Sheni. ומה מעשר הקל, u-mah
ma'aser hakal, מעשר שני, Ma'aser Sheni, אוכלין חוץ לחומה לוקה, ochlin chutz
lachomah lokeh, I know that that, this is like מעשר שני, Ma'aser
Sheni, the פשט pshat of the פסוק pasuk before we said it
was טבל tevel but it didn't have מעשר עני ma'aser ani taken
from it. Okay, but from the beginning of the פסוק, pasuk, I
know that you get lashes for eating מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni out
of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So certainly you'll get lashes—now of course there's a
problem about, you know, using a קל וחומר kal vachomer to learn
lashes, מזהירין מן הדין, mazhirin min hadin, we'll get to that. But
if you get lashes for מעשר שני, Ma'aser Sheni, certainly you get
lashes for eating ביכורים bikkurim out of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. ומה מעשר הקל
אוכלין חוץ לחומה לוקה, ביכורים לא כל שכן? u-mah ma'aser hakal ochlin
chutz lachomah lokeh, bikkurim lo kol shekein? Okay, now what the קל
וחומר kal vachomer is, we'll see in the גמרא, Gemara, but he
assumes that ביכורים bikkurim is weightier than מעשר שני. Ma'aser Sheni. הלא
בא הכתוב אלא לאכול ביכורים עד שלא קרא עליהם שלוקה. Halo ba
hakatuv ela le'echol bikkurim ad shelo kara aleihem shelokeh. So this is
telling you something else about ביכורים. bikkurim. Not מעשר, ma'aser, this is
מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni out of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. The פשט pshat of
the whole פסוק pasuk is, all of this is out of ירושלים.
Yerushalayim. But he says once you know, here's the basic point, that
מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni you get lashes out of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, all
the other stuff is weightier than מעשר שני. Ma'aser Sheni. So of
course you would get lashes for this other stuff out of ירושלים.
Yerushalayim. So if it's saying you get lashes because that's the negative
prohibition, it's saying you get lashes for another problem, not the out
of ירושלים Yerushalayim problem. So what's the problem with ביכורים? bikkurim? The
problem is not out of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, the problem with ביכורים bikkurim
is before the declaration. Okay, that's by the way where we started.
You could have said before it was put down. That's the debate
of what you need to make the ביכורים bikkurim permissible: the declaration
or the putting it down. Okay, and when they go through the
whole list and say all this stuff is weightier, you know, and
we could have known that it was automatically forbidden. So if it's
still being mentioned, the problem is not just that it's out of
ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Okay. So, לאכול ביכורים, le'echol bikkurim, ונדבותיך זו תודה ושלמים,
u-nedavotecha zo todah u-shelamim, that you can't eat a תודה todah and
שלמים shelamim out of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. אמר רבי שמעון מה בא זה
ללמדנו? Amar Rebbe Shimon ma ba zeh lelamdenu? What does this teach
us? אם לאוכלן חוץ לחומה, im le'ochlan chutz lachomah, if it's saying
you can't eat out of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, קל וחומר ממעשר. kal vachomer
mima'aser. So you can't eat מעשר ma'aser out of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, you
can't eat קרבנות korbanot out of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. הלא בא הכתוב אלא
לאכול בתודה ושלמים לפני זריקה שלוקה. Halo ba hakatuv ela le'echol be-todah
u-shelamim lifnei zerikah shelokeh. Similar to this idea of what we said
by ביכורים, bikkurim, it's before the right time, before the thing that
makes it permissible. Okay. Do
we know that from other sources also? We know that you have
to wait, but we know it's an עשה. aseh. This is telling
us that it's a לא תעשה. lo ta'aseh. So what Michael said
is correct and רש״י Rashi points it out, a number of these
things we already know that this is a requirement, okay, but what
we don't know is that you transgress a negative prohibition and you
violate this requirement and you get מלכות. malkus. So by taking things
we already know are problematic and putting them in this פסוק, pasuk,
we're allowing you to get lashes for them, to make it a
negative prohibition. Okay. So this he says is basically שלמים, shelamim, you
know, קדשים קלים, kodashim kalim, and what is the problem? The problem
is not out of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, but again, anybody remember that ad
on TV, I'm really dating myself, we will sell no wine before
its time? Remember that?
No? Anyway, we will eat no קרבן korban or whatever, all these
are problems because it's before its time, not because of the location
but because of the time. So here it was before the declaration,
here it is before the זריקת הדם. zerikat hadam.
Okay. And therefore you get lashes, that's what that's coming to teach
us. Let's keep on looking.
ובכורות, U-vechorot, so he's actually not making a difference between
נדרים ונדבות, nedarim u-nedavot, that's interesting, okay, as it's all basically קדשים
קלים. kodashim kalim.
ובכורות זה בכור. U-vechorot zeh bechor. Okay, that you can't eat a
בכור bechor out of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. אמר רבי שמעון Amar Rebbe Shimon,
מה בא זה ללמדנו? Ma ba zeh lelamdenu? What is this teaching
us? אם לאוכלן חוץ לחומה, Im le'ochlan chutz lachomah, don't eat a
בכור bechor out of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, קל וחומר ממעשר. kal vachomer mima'aser.
אם לפני זריקה, Im lifnei zerikah, now there's a reason why he's
working backwards, right? Why did he work down or why did he
work up? Why did he work backward? Because he wanted to first
establish that a lighter thing like, well, he wanted to first establish
that this can't eat before זריקת הדם. zerikat hadam. Once he's established
this, he says well that would also include בכור bechor from a
קל וחומר. kal vachomer. Why this is weightier than a בכור bechor
is not clear. But once this idea before זריקה zerikah now is
covered, this is telling you something even more than the before זריקה
zerikah problem. הלא בא הכתוב אלא לאכול מן הבכור אפילו לאחר זריקה
שלוקה. Halo ba hakatuv ela le'echol min habechor afilu le-achar zerikah shelokeh.
Okay, this is to tell you that you get lashes even after
the זריקה. zerikah. Now what do you mean? After the זריקה zerikah
you're allowed to eat from it. Right, okay, so this is a
problem by the בכור, bechor, it's a problem about a, if it's
a non-כהן. kohen. So we know a non-כהן kohen can't eat the
בכור. bechor. Again, we know these things, but we don't know it's
a לאו תעשה. lav ta'aseh. We don't know you get lashes, okay?
So yes, all these things we know they're a problem, but we
don't know that you get lashes for them, alright? So we already
know you can't eat from קרבנות korbanot before the זריקת הדם. zerikat
hadam. The בכור bechor is telling you even if it was זריקת
הדם zerikat hadam but you're a non-כהן. kohen. That's what you get
from בכור. bechor. Does it also include putting whatever part of the
meats or חלבים chalavim you need to put on the altar? Because
that just is not the הלכה halacha that you can't eat the
meat from after זריקת הדם. zerikat hadam. Okay, but from the other
ones, I mean after זריקה. zerika. He's not coming to be מחדש
mechadesh a הלכה halacha in the sense of what are the requirements,
he's coming to tell you that you get lashes when you violate
those requirements. Okay, you're right, all of the things he's coming with
a pre-existing understanding of what the requirements are and then he's just
plugging into the פסוק pasuk that when you violate them you get
these lashes. Okay. ובבקרך וצאנך Uvevarkacha vetzonacha now we could not get
נדריך ונדבותיך, nedarecha unidvotecha, all of these leaves us in the קדשים
קלים kodashim kalim area, okay? Because these are all just normal lighter
sacrifices. But ובקרך וצאנך, uvkarcha vetzonacha, which just says animals, if you
cut it away from the first half of the פסוק, pasuk, that
can talk about קדשי קדשים. kodshei kodashim. That can talk about the
weightier sacrifices like a חטאת. chatat. Okay, so this is קדשי קדשים
kodshei kodashim like a חטאת chatat would be an example. Okay, so
what's going to be the problem eating from that? Okay, so what
is that? Where were we? אמר רבי שמעון זו חטאת ואשם. Amar
Rabbi Shimon zo chatat ve'asham. אמר רבי שמעון מה בא זה ללמדנו?
אם לאוכלן חוץ לחומה קל וחומר ממעשר Amar Rabbi Shimon ma ba
ze lelamdenu? Im lochlan chutz lachoma kal vachomer mima'aser you don't eat
it out of the walls. אם לפני זריקה קל וחומר מתודה ושלמים
Im lifnei zerika kal vachomer mitoda u'shlamim don't eat before the blood
is thrown. אם לאחר זריקה Im le'achar zerika after the blood is
thrown so it's מותר mutar now as a קרבן, korban, it's gotten
to the next stage, קל וחומר מבכור. kal vachomer mibechor. Okay, but
you're not a כהן, kohen, so we know from a בכור bechor
don't eat it. אם חוץ לקלעים Im chutz lakla'im if it's outside
of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, out of the, like, the curtains
is literally what that means, קל וחומר מחטאת ואשם. kal vachomer mechatat
ve'asham. So, okay, from a חטאת ואשם chatat ve'asham I know that
you have to eat it in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Of
course, an עולה olah can't be eaten at all. הלא לא בא
הכתוב אלא ללמדנו אלא Halo lo ba hakatuv ela lelamdenu ela see,
I thought we weren't going to finish the דף daf today אלא
לאכול מן העולה לאחר זריקה אפילו בפנים שהוא לוקה. ela leechol min
ha'olah le'achar zerika afilu bifnim shehu loke. So an עולה, olah, nobody
can eat an עולה, olah, even if you're a כהן kohen and
even if it's אחר זריקה achar zerika and even if it's in
the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, you're not allowed to eat it. כהן,
Kohen, don't eat it. Period, don't eat an עולה. olah. Okay, so
all of these are not just telling you don't eat out of
ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Once you say don't eat מעשר ma'aser out of ירושלים,
Yerushalayim, you know don't eat all of this. All these are telling
you don't eat these various קרבנות korbanot in ways we know you're
not supposed to eat them already. Okay? You're not a כהן, kohen,
it's before זריקת הדם, zerikat hadam, it's out of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, it's
out of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, it's an עולה. olah. And
if you eat them in ways we know you're not supposed to
be eating them, you get lashes. That's what רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
says. Alright. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this, אמר רבא.
Amar Rava. But by the way, along the way he said the
importance of בכורים bikurim was the declaration, not the putting down, remember
that's how we started the discussion. That for בכורים bikurim the מתיר
matir is the declaration. אמר רבא Amar Rava says רבא, Rava, very
cute גמרא Gemara here. דילדי אימיה כרבי שמעון תילד, Deyaldei imei k'Rabbi
Shimon teyalad, if your mother gives birth to you, the one whose
mother gives birth to him she should give birth like רבי שמעון.
Rabbi Shimon. Meaning, like you said, you should have a kid like
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon or you should be זכה zoche to have
a mother like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon so you should be a
רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. This was like brilliant what רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon did, the way he דרש darshened the פסוק, pasuk, the way
he layered it, establishing one and then moving on to the next.
So he was able to establish all of these different things are
being referred to in the פסוק. pasuk. Okay? ואי לא לא תילד,
V'ilo lo teyalad, if your mom isn't going to have a רבי
שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, better she shouldn't have at all. Okay? ואף על
גב דאית ליה פירכא, V'af al gav d'is lei pircha, this was
brilliant even though I could challenge everything you just said. Fine, I
could challenge it, it doesn't matter, it's still brilliant. Okay? But all
of your קל וחומר, kal vachomers, right, the way he knew it
couldn't be talking about out of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, it could, because it
was all everything was a קל וחומר kal vachomer from everything that
preceded. He says all the קל וחומר kal vachomers can be challenged.
How can the קל וחומר kal vachomers be challenged? מאי חומרא דבכורים?
Mai chumra d'bikurim? We said if מעשר maaser is אסור assur out
of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, בכורים bikurim is אסור assur out of ירושלים Yerushalayim
because of a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. What makes us assume that
בכורים bikurim is weightier than מעשר? maaser? שכן אסורים לזרים, Shekein assurim
lezarim, because בכורים bikurim is like תרומה, terumah, it can't be eaten
by non-כהנים, kohanim, so it's clearly weightier than מעשר שני. Maaser Sheni.
מעשר שני Maaser Sheni can be eaten by non-כהנים. kohanim. That was
his קל וחומר. kal vachomer. So if מעשר שני Maaser Sheni has
to be eaten in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, certainly בכורים. bikurim. One minute, there's
ways מעשר שני Maaser Sheni is weightier. So אדרבה, adaraba, מעשר חמור
שכן אסור לאונן. maaser chamur shekein assur leonein. If somebody has just
suffered a loss, a family member died, by מעשר maaser you're not
supposed, לא אכלתי באוני ממנו, lo achalti be'oni mimenu, you can't eat
it when you're an אונן. onein. Okay? But בכורים, bikurim, ironically, can
be eaten for an אונן. onein. So even though it's a minor
point, it's enough that it's not a total קל וחומר. kal vachomer.
Just because you transgressed by מעשר maaser out of ירושלים Yerushalayim doesn't
mean you would transgress by בכורים. bikurim. בכורים bikurim is not across
the board weightier. Okay? ומאי חומרא דתודה ושלמים? U'mai chumra d'todah v'shelamim?
Now once we know right that you can't eat you know מעשר
maaser out of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, we know you can't eat תודה ושלמים,
todah v'shelamim, קדשים קלים kodshim kalim out of ירושלים Yerushalayim from the
same קל וחומר. kal vachomer. So what makes קדשים קלים kodshim kalim
weightier than מעשר שני? Maaser Sheni? ממעשר שכן טעונים מתן דמים ואימורין
לגבי מזבח. mi'maaser shekein te'unim matan damim v'eimurin legabei mizbe'ach. It's obvious,
I mean, you know, they bring you have to bring it as
a קרבן. korban. I mean already that's you know, and there's a
lot of other הלכות halachos about the fact that it's sanctified that
makes it weightier than מעשר שני. Maaser Sheni. So of course you
have to eat it in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. But one minute, אדרבה, adaraba,
מעשר חמור שכן טעונים כסף צורה. maaser chamur shekein te'unim keseph tzurah.
Again, it's a relatively trivial point. When you redeem מעשר, maaser, you
need it to be on a coin that has an image. And
whereas when you redeem קרבנות, korbanot, I know, when you redeem קרבנות
korbanot you don't have to be on a coin that has an
image. So it's a very minor technical point, but okay, there's a
way in which מעשר maaser is weightier. So you can't make, a
קל וחומר kal vachomer assumes that something is across the board you
know like one is across the board weaker and one is across
the board weightier. And here it's not true that מעשר maaser is
across the board weaker. So you can't really make that קל וחומר.
kal vachomer. ומאי חומרא דבכור מתודה ושלמים? U'mai chumra d'bechor mi'todah v'shelamim?
Then we said oh, and what בכור, bechor, you know, once a
תודה ושלמים todah v'shelamim you can't eat before זריקה, zrika, certainly you
בכור bechor you can't because a בכור bechor is weightier. What makes
the בכור bechor weightier? It's all קדשים קלים kodshim kalim than a
תודה ושלמים. todah v'shelamim. שכן קדושתו מרחם, Shekein kedushaso merachem, because it
is sanctified automatically from the womb. You don't even need to verbally
sanctify it, it's automatically sanctified. That means that it's weightier, it already
starts its life as holy. אדרבה, adaraba, תודה ושלמים חמור. todah v'shelamim
chamur. No, I'll tell you ways in which תודה ושלמים todah v'shelamim
is weightier. שכן טעונים סמיכה ונסכים ותנופה חזה ושוק. Shekein te'unim smeicha
v'nesachim v'tnufa chazeh v'shok. That's already not just a trivial point. The
way in which the קרבן korban is brought is way much more
ritual. Like you put your hands on it, you bring the the
wine and the flour together with it, you wave it, you give
the חזה ושוק chazeh v'shok to the כהן. kohen. Okay? So you
said oh, because שלמים shelamim you can't eat before זריקה, zrika, certainly
a בכור bechor you can't eat before זריקה. zrika. And you learned
בכור bechor to tell you the idea of a non-כהן. kohen. No,
you can't make a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. There's ways in which
בכור bechor is not as weighty as תודה ושלמים. todah v'shelamim. Okay,
now, ומאי חומרא דחטאת ואשם מבכור? u'mai chumra d'chatas v'asham mi'bechor? Then
once we know right that a בכור bechor can't be eaten by
you know a non-כהן kohen and you get lashes, we said certainly
a חטאת, chatas, you know you would get lashes of a non-כהן.
kohen. And with חטאת chatas we learned that you get lashes if
it's out of the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. So it's a קל
וחומר. kal vachomer. If it's true by a בכור, bechor, it's true
by a חטאת. chatas. Okay? So ומאי חומרא דחטאת ואשם מבכור? u'mai
chumra d'chatas v'asham mi'bechor? שכן קדשי קדשים, Shekein kodshei kodashim, because חטאת
chatas and אשם asham are the holiest sacrifices, only eaten by כהנים,
kohanim, only eaten in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. אדרבה בכור חמור,
Adaraba bechor chamur, I'll have you a way in which a בכור
bechor is weightier. שכן קדושתו מרחם. Shekein kedushaso merachem. Now it's a
relatively trivial point, but okay, it's קדוש kadosh from the moment that
it's born. So again, just because something is אסור assur by בכור
bechor doesn't mean that it's forbidden by a חטאת chatas and an
אשם. asham. ומה חומרא דעולה מחטאת ואשם? Umah chumrah de'olah michatas ve'asham?
Then we get, once חטאת chatas and אשם, asham, you get lashes
out of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, certainly an עולה. olah. And
that's the extra thing that an עולה olah is prohibiting is don't
eat it at all. What makes an עולה olah weightier than a
חטאת chatas and an אשם? asham? Okay, שכן כליל, she-ken kalil, that
it's all burnt on the מזבח mizbei'ach on the altar. אדרבה חטאת
ואשם חמיר שכן מכפרי. Adaraba chatas ve'asham chamir she-ken mechafrei. חטאת Chatas
and אשם asham are weightier, they atone, and עולה olah isn't brought
for atoning. So this was brilliant that you learned all this stuff
we already know is a problem and by layering it you learned
that every one of them gets lashes, but it's all based on
an assumption of a קל וחומר, kal vechomer, that if you say
it by A, it's true about the rest. So the next thing
is coming to tell you something new. So he says every קל
וחומר, kal vechomer, it's not a it's not a definite קל וחומר,
kal vechomer, it's not absolutely weightier or stronger. ביטול עשה bitul asei
or on a ביטול עשה? bitul asei? Yeah, but not to the
same degree. Okay, לכולהו, le-kuleihu, it's not מכפר mechaper on a לא
תעשה. lo sa'asei. לכולהו חמירי מעולה, le-kuleihu chamiri mei-olah, and not only
that, you know, one way is saying that עולה olah is weightier
because it's all burnt. Say it the opposite: everything else is weightier
than עולה, olah, דאית בהו שתי אכילות, de-is be-hu shtei achilos, because
it's both consumed on the מזבח mizbei'ach and consumed by the כהנים
kohanim or by the owners. Maybe that makes it weightier than the
עולה, olah, not the reverse? אלא, Ela, okay, so therefore, yes it
was brilliant, but it doesn't hold water. אלא מאי דילדה אמיה כרבי
שמעון? Ela mai de-yalda imei ke-Rabbi Shimon? So why was he so
brilliant? Why oh, whoever's mother gives birth to him should give birth
to him like רבי שמעון? Rabbi Shimon? דלמא דסבירא ליה לדידיה, delama
de-savira lei le-didei, because the way what he held, he held it
was all a קל וחומר. kal vechomer. מסרסיה לקרא ודריש ליה. mesarsia
le-kora ve-darish lei. He figured out that if you interpret the פסוק
pasuk and you work from the back and reverse, you'll be able
to layer it to get to these conclusions. If you started in
the right order, you never would have got that way. But by
starting at the end and working backwards, it basically was ingenious the
way he did it even if it doesn't really hold water. Okay,
now the גמרא Gemara has one final question. The גמרא Gemara says
like this, וכי מזהירין מן הדין? ve-chi mazhirin min hadin? Forget the
קל וחומר kal vechomer problem. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says once I
know מעשר ma'aser is אסור assur outside ירושלים, Yerushalayim, I know it
by all the rest. And therefore it's coming to tell me something,
once it's true you know, he assumed that the קל וחומר kal
vechomer would extend the prohibition to the other things in the list
because of a קל וחומר. kal vechomer. But we have a principle,
you can't warn, you can't prohibit something based on a קל וחומר.
kal vechomer. There are two principles: אין עונשין מן הדין, ein onshin
min hadin, if we know something is prohibited we can't give you
a punishment based on a קל וחומר. kal vechomer. Oh, well you
get a punishment for that עבירה, aveira, you're going to get a
punishment for this עבירה. aveira. That question of אין עונשין מן הדין
ein onshin min hadin is debated. But אין מזהירין מן הדין, ein
mazhirin min hadin, which is if we don't yet know that it's
a prohibition, I can't make it prohibited based on a קל וחומר,
kal vechomer, everybody agrees to that. So there's another huge problem here.
He said oh once I know it's true by מעשר, ma'aser, I
know it's true by this or something else, once I know it's
true here it's true here. No, you can't make something prohibited based
on a קל וחומר! kal vechomer! So his whole point falls apart.
Okay, וכי מזהירין מן הדין? ve-chi mazhirin min hadin? הא אפילו למאן
דאמר עונשין מן הדין, ha afilu le-man de-amar onshin min hadin, even
if you could get a punishment from a קל וחומר kal vechomer
once you know that something is forbidden, the punishment might be able
to be learned out from a קל וחומר, kal vechomer, אין מזהירין
מן הדין. ein mazhirin min hadin. Everybody agrees that you can't be
prohibited based on a קל וחומר, kal vechomer, so how did he
do this? Okay, so what if it's a קל וחומר? kal vechomer?
Would it make it forbidden? So the גמרא Gemara says איסורא בעלמא.
issura be'alma. All right, what he meant is if I knew that
it was אסור assur for מעשר, ma'aser, I would have known the
rest was אסור. assur. I wouldn't have said you got lashes and
it was a biblical transgression, I would use the קל וחומר kal
vechomer to say that it was אסור. assur. But that's not what
he's saying. But the whole point is to say you get lashes,
which is what the גמרא Gemara says. No, you can't say that.
ואמר רבא, ve-amar Rava, זר שאכל מן העולה לפני זריקה חוץ לחומה
לרבי שמעון לוקה חמש. zar she-achal min ha-olah lifnei zrika chutz la-choma
le-Rabbi Shimon lokei chamesh. The whole point is that you do get
lashes. This whole דרשה drasha is to say you got lashes. Now,
why לוקה חמש? lokei chamesh? It's like eating the ant, you get
five. Because if you ate the עולה olah before זריקה, zrika, out
of whatever, you have the prohibition of eating an עולה, olah, you
have the prohibition of eating out of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash,
you have the prohibition of a זר, zar, non-כהן, kohen, you have
the prohibition of eating before זריקה zrika stuff, right? All of those
prohibitions, say, apply to the weightier things on the list. Okay, you
got the idea? So it's not just this is one thing, the
whole point of his קל וחומר kal vechomer is that every thing
that's weightier gets all the earlier prohibitions and you get lashes. So
clearly he is saying you get lashes. What about the problem that
you can't say that based on a קל וחומר? kal vechomer? Okay,
חמשה איסורין הוו. chamisha issurin havo. No, it doesn't mean five lashes,
it means you did five transgressions but not lashes. But that's not
what he's saying. והאנן תנן אלו הן הלוקין. ve-ha'anan tenan elu hein
halokin. Our משנה, mishna, and one of the things our משנה... mishna...
lists, is like the ביכורים Bikkurim and some of this stuff, is
about getting lashes. Don't tell me lashes doesn't mean lashes. רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon is telling me you get lashes for all this stuff.
What about the fact that you're not supposed to be able to
know that from a קל וחומר? kal vachomer? So אלא, ella, here's
the punchline. קרא יתירה הוא. kra yesera hu. The verse is extra.
מכדי כתיב והבאתם שמה—this michdi ksiv ve-heveisa sham whole verse. Because all
these particulars were mentioned in the positive in a previous verse. The
earlier verse says, והבאתם שמה, ve-heveisa sham, you'll bring this to ירושלים,
Yerushalayim, ואכלת לפני ה' אלהיך במקום אשר יבחר מעשר דגנך תירשך ויצהרך
ובכרת בקרך וצאנך וכל נדריך אשר תדר ונדבתיך ותרומת ידך. ve-achalta lifnei
Hashem Elokecha bamakom asher yivchar ma'asar degancha tiroshcha ve-yitzharecha u-vechoros bekarcha ve-tzoncha
ve-chol nedarecha asher tidor ve-nidvosecha u-serumas yadecha. Exactly everything in this list
an earlier פסוק pasuk says eat it in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So when
it got to say don't eat it out of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, you
know what it could have said? לא תוכל לאכלם. lo tuchal le-ochlam.
You know, לא תוכל לאכול אותם חוץ לשעריך. lo tuchal le-echol osam
chutz lish'arecha. It could have had one word, them. And instead, it
lists the individual things. Okay. ליכתוב רחמנא לא תוכל לאכלם. lichtav rachmana
lo tuchal le-ochlam. When it wanted to say don't do it, it
could have just said them. מהא דמפרש בה רחמנא למה לי? mi-had
d-mifaresh bei rachmana lama li? Why does it say a word, a
repeat every single word? Okay. אלא ליחודי להו לאו לכל חד וחד.
ella liyachudei lehu lav l'chol chad ve-chad. In order to give each
one a new לאו. lav. So it means like this. If it
was just a general קל וחומר, kal vachomer, there was some פסוק
pasuk that said don't eat מעשר ma'aser out of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, I
couldn't say, oh, now you'll also get lashes for eating a בכור
bechor out of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. I couldn't say that. That's just getting
lashes or you know, making something forbidden based on a קל וחומר.
kal vachomer. But that's not his point. His point is, why does
it repeat each word? It repeats each word to teach you that
there's another לאו lav that exists here. Okay. If it just wanted
to say one whatever, it would have just said them. Because it
repeats each word, it's coming to tell you every word is telling
you that there's a new prohibition that applies to this thing and
the things that are weightier than it. Okay. So the general rule
is you don't just find something that's forbidden and say oh קל
וחומר kal vachomer this other thing is forbidden as well. But because
here every single word is extra, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon approaches this
and says, I think each word is teaching you a new prohibition,
and the point is that that new prohibition applies to the word
it said by and to everything that's weightier than that category as
well. Okay, so that's his special דרשה. drasha. So again, what רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon gets from this דרשה drasha is all these things
that we already knew were forbidden, he says they all of them
have separate איסורין, issurin, lashes, and lashes for them and for the
stuff that's weightier than they. Okay, and that he gets all on
that פסוק. pasuk. And the גמרא Gemara though says that was brilliant,
but you know, the קל וחומר kal vachomer don't exactly work. Does
that mean we disagree with the הלכה? halacha? That's not exactly clear,
but for רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon like רבא Rava says, you can
eat or whoever it was said, you can eat one thing, the
same way you get five lashes for an ant, you get five
lashes for one thing because it transgresses, you know, multiple prohibitions in
this פסוק. pasuk. Okay. All right, so that's what we will end
with for today.